<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Porting Printing to Zephyr - GSoC 2025</title>
    <link>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Porting Printing to Zephyr - GSoC 2025</description>
    <image>
      <title>Porting Printing to Zephyr - GSoC 2025</title>
      <url>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/images/openprintingzephyr.png</url>
      <link>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/images/openprintingzephyr.png</link>
    </image>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.147.6</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Hubert Guan, OpenPrinting, Zephyr</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2025 18:05:27 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Week 1: PDFio and zlib</title>
      <link>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/posts/week1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2025 18:05:27 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/posts/week1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Now that this inaugural week is done, I have some time to reflect on what I’ve learned and what did/did not go well. I’ve learned that I definitely work best at the beginning of my day, as I can basically devote my time entirely to the project for a few hours before dealing with other things and working more intermittently throughout pretty much the rest of the day. However, there are some things that can distract me from keeping up the momentum for those first few hours. Therefore, I think that starting work earlier and adapting my environment to be free of those distractions is something I should look towards.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Porting Printing to Zephyr</title>
      <link>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/posts/intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 15:17:36 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/posts/intro/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;OpenPrinting and Zephyr&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/images/openprintingzephyr.png#center&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;about-the-project&#34;&gt;About the Project&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Printers are a technology that we often think should “just work,” but in reality, there are often many hoops to jump through when dealing with a printer’s drivers. It is a common experience when dealing with printers to struggle to get a document printed when trying every which way on an OS like modern Windows, but then all the problems suddenly disappear when using an Apple device. This is in large part thanks to Apple’s AirPrint, which is the oldest and most widely supported driverless printing protocol. The driverless nature is important as it prevents the issue of having printer drivers that may not be updated to support the user’s current operating system. However, AirPrint is not an open standard, and only Apple operating systems are designed with it in mind. This leads us to IPP Everywhere, a driverless printing protocol that is an open standard, and its pivotal role in the modern open-source printing stack developed by OpenPrinting. This would theoretically allow any operating system that supports the printing stack to print, as long as the printer supports IPP Everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
