<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Porting Printing to Zephyr - GSoC 2025</title>
    <link>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Porting Printing to Zephyr - GSoC 2025</description>
    <image>
      <title>Porting Printing to Zephyr - GSoC 2025</title>
      <url>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/images/openprintingzephyr.png</url>
      <link>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/images/openprintingzephyr.png</link>
    </image>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.147.6</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Hubert Guan, OpenPrinting, Zephyr</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 01:35:03 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Week 17/18: Testing with the New Memory Management Scheme</title>
      <link>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/posts/weeks17-18/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 01:35:03 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/posts/weeks17-18/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I had to combine these two weeks into one report since I generally do not have much time to work during the first half of the week since that’s when I have to spend the most time on schoolwork (now that the academic term has fully begun). I was able to focus on testing during the last few days and have discovered some important information, and I should be able to progress to testing PAPPL relatively soon.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Week 16: ippeveprinter Woes and Updated Plans</title>
      <link>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/posts/week16/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 00:26:46 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/posts/week16/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;From what I could gather this week when working on ippeveprinter, it is likely not going to be running on Zephyr any time soon. The reality is that ippeveprinter is 8k lines of code without some kind of modular testbench and that it is clearly not written for embedded systems (besides embedded Linux devices, which have traits of traditional computer systems). It has also become a debugging nightmare to get through since logs are not clear as to what exactly is going wrong and there is not much comparison with regular ippeveprinter on Linux since most of the logs disappear if nothing goes wrong. Furthermore, step-through debugging is not the best when testing a real-time connection HTTP connection that can timeout. Lastly, it takes a lot of overhead time just to reset my testing setup since &lt;code&gt;ippfind&lt;/code&gt; can often have trouble finding ippeveprinter.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Week 15: More pthread and Memory Adventures in ippeveprinter</title>
      <link>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/posts/week15/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:47:49 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/posts/week15/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week has definitely had many ups and downs in terms of this project and my work now that I am officially starting my Fall quarter. Surprisingly (or unsurprisingly due to reasons I will get into), I have not had that much time to work on this project despite classes being basically nonexistent in terms of assignments (with the exception of the embedded systems course ECE 153a that makes me go into Vivado even before the first lecture). The main thing that has been taking up my time is working on a new initiative with the ACM student chapter at UCSB, which involves managing communications with much of the faculty from two departments and many meetings for event planning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Week 14: ippeveprinter Configuration, DNS-SD, and HTTP</title>
      <link>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/posts/week14/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 16:07:55 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/posts/week14/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I had more time this week to work on and debug the DNS-SD services and functionality of ippeveprinter. I was able to figure out how to get ippeveprinter recognized as a printer by CUPS, but I’ve also had a lot more issues with processing jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I noticed that I have to load a &lt;code&gt;test.conf&lt;/code&gt; file, or else seemingly every job will fail when running on my local machine. It turns out that the &lt;code&gt;load_ippserver_attributes&lt;/code&gt; is very memory-intensive, and I was only able to get it to work after increasing a bunch of stack sizes in the kconfig (see &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/HubertYGuan/zephyr-example/blob/main/prj.conf&#34;&gt;source code&lt;/a&gt;). This means that I have only about 5% of my DRAM available for the heap, and I am also unsure if my pthread stacks are large enough to handle the HTTP functions either.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Week 13: Short ippeveprinter Update</title>
      <link>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/posts/week13/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 22:16:36 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/posts/week13/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As I alluded to in my previous post, I did not have much time to work on ippeveprinter this week, but I did manage to figure out what was wrong before. Now, mostly DNS-SD and networking work remains to be done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for the previous issue I faced, I figured out that it was caused by a lack of available stack memory for &lt;code&gt;ippeve_main&lt;/code&gt; and that I actually had to &lt;code&gt;malloc&lt;/code&gt; the stack myself since the default &lt;code&gt;pthread_attr&lt;/code&gt; allocation method conflicts with the net management allocations for some reason (if I allocate one, the other will fail to allocate unless I set the stack size low enough).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Week 12: More Debugging</title>
      <link>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/posts/week12/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 23:41:54 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/posts/week12/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Although I was not able to work very much this week, I was able to delve further into running ippeveprinter, and I also have an update on JTAG debugging. I was able to resolve the previous issues about pthreads for now, as well as most of my previous issues with debugging, but there is now a whole new suite of issues for me to deal with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;ippeveprinter&#34;&gt;ippeveprinter&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After running ippeveprinter in a pthread, I noticed that I would either get stuck somewhere spinning indefinitely or get the following store-prohibited error:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Week 11: ippeveprinter Continued</title>
      <link>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/posts/week11/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 18:56:48 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/posts/week11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week was mainly spent trying to figure out all of the small issues in trying to translate ippeveprinter and libcups functionality over from Linux. I’ve learned more about how Zephyr handles concepts like pthreads and how they can be a lot more difficult to deal with than on Linux. I also recently received my ESP32s3 board, so I have also been testing the application there as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;ippeveprinter-update&#34;&gt;ippeveprinter Update&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily, it seems that using the previously mentioned syscalls like &lt;code&gt;pipe&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;dup&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;execve&lt;/code&gt; are not entirely necessary for the functioning of ippeveprinter since those are only used to execute user-defined bash commands for incoming print jobs. However, something else has become the main problem with implementing the rest of ippeveprinter: pthreads. Since libcups uses pthread keys to manage its globals, I’ve had issues every time I’ve tried to initiate and store globals. Mainly, &lt;code&gt;pthread_setspecific&lt;/code&gt; will return &lt;code&gt;EINVAL&lt;/code&gt; since &lt;code&gt;to_posix_thread(pthread_self())&lt;/code&gt; will fail. Inside of &lt;code&gt;pthread_self&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Week 10: DNS-SD and ippeveprinter</title>
      <link>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/posts/week10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2025 16:42:28 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/posts/week10/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week, I put the JTAG debugging and the rest of the libcups tests on hold in favor of getting ippeveprinter (a minimal print server example) up and running on Zephyr. Generally, what I have been seeing myself doing through this process and stage of development is removing all of the parts that would not be feasible to support right now and focusing on the actual application rather than all of the tests for libraries. This is because it’s become clear to me that time is going to be scarce over the next weeks as I have finals for my summer classes and then a significantly more difficult Fall term after that.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Week 9: Debugging and mDNS Responder</title>
      <link>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/posts/week9/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 18:35:30 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/posts/week9/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week has definitely been less straightforward than the previous weeks as I continue testing libcups and figuring out a clear path forward for what needs to be ported and what can be left out. I have continued with getting through the other tests for libcups (at least the ones relevant to the print server application), exploring mDNS Responder use in libcups, and I have also been working on getting OpenOCD debugging with my debugger board.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Week 8: libcups Updates</title>
      <link>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/posts/week8/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 12:35:23 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/posts/week8/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As I alluded to in my previous post, I am now back in Santa Barbara (or rather Goleta). This means I have some additional resources from my lab and professors, but also a lot of additional responsibilities from my classes, dealing with my apartment, etc. This means that I will have a smaller amount of time to work on GSoC, but I will make sure to work on the project as much as I can and continue to keep you all updated.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Week 7: Midterm Update</title>
      <link>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/posts/week7/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 14:08:05 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/posts/week7/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Now that midterm evaluations have come out, it is time to reflect on my experiences and the progress that I’ve made. Overall, I am proud of the progress that I have made, but I know that there is a lot more work left to do. For this week, I have been able to get a test suite running for libcups. However, there is a lot more testing to be done since libcups is a lot more complex and less self-contained than other libraries like zlib or pdfio.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Week 6: More Progress on libcups</title>
      <link>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/posts/week6/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 21:10:09 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/posts/week6/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Although libcups has been the most challenging project to port and has taken a lot longer than I initially thought, I feel like I am finally a lot closer to getting the library operational. Even though I am not quite done with getting everything prepared for compilation unlike what I said I would do earlier, I have gone through and added code for all of the parts where Mbed TLS is needed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Week 5: libcups Continued</title>
      <link>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/posts/week5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 16:56:01 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/posts/week5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week was again spent mostly on refactoring libcups to support Mbed TLS, and besides some slight issues, I should be able to finish implementing it soon and then make some additional header files (or forks) to implement the rest of the functionality needed from libc and mDNS Responder so that I can get a test application to compile. Another thing to note is that I feel like I have learned a lot about TLS and cryptography just from working with Mbed TLS. I used to not pay too much attention to the field of cryptography in my work and research, but now I realize more and more that cryptography is definitely relevant to this field of embedded systems and my research in computer architecture.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Week 4: libcups and Dependencies</title>
      <link>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/posts/week4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 11:52:45 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/posts/week4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I want to start by saying that porting libcups is significantly more complex than porting zlib or PDFio, and I was definitely wrong in saying that I could port it quickly. Although setting up the build scripts and environment is relatively simple, like with zlib and PDFio, I also have to make significant additions and changes to the source code in multiple libraries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;mbed-tls&#34;&gt;Mbed TLS&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first challenge comes in the form of Zephyr’s TLS library, Mbed TLS. Since the design methodologies of OpenSSL, GNU TLS, and Mbed TLS differ, I first had to modify Mbed TLS to expose previously static functions (mainly for &lt;code&gt;cupsAreCredentialsValidForName&lt;/code&gt;). Since the contributors didn’t want users to have access to functions like &lt;code&gt;x509_crt_verify_name&lt;/code&gt; that are practically needed to implement some of the libcups functions (maybe due to security concerns), this sort of modification is unofficial and can be quite murky.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Week 3: PDFio and zlib Updates</title>
      <link>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/posts/week3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Jul 2025 20:17:23 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/posts/week3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week marks the point where zlib and PDFio are wrapped up for now. This update is fairly short since there has not been a lot of new stuff going on this week, since most of the work has been with testing, and I celebrated Independence Day last Friday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can now proudly say that zlib passes the provided &lt;code&gt;example&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;infcover&lt;/code&gt; tests at least on the ESP32. Luckily, I did not have to go digging around in GDB very much since the problems seemed to just be in the compile options and library choice. Now that I have enforced the &lt;code&gt;_POSIX_C_SOURCE&lt;/code&gt; parameter and switched to newlib, things have been going fine so far.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Week 2: PDFio and zlib Continued</title>
      <link>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/posts/week2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Jun 2025 21:40:07 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/posts/week2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week was mainly a continuation of my work during week 1. I continued work on zlib by conducting more rigorous testing, covering the relevant tests within the default CMakeLists. Overall, I think that zlib is mostly functional at the current state and should provide general compression and decompression functionality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;notes-on-zlib&#34;&gt;Notes on zlib&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are still some things to keep in mind on the current state of zlib; first of which is building the test application, especially since I have to use a file system like littlefs. In &lt;code&gt;gzlib.c&lt;/code&gt; and related source files for “gz” prefixed functions, file i/o functionality is required, and I figured that littlefs would be a good fit since it is designed for use in embedded applications. However, it seems that some platforms, such as my &lt;code&gt;native_sim&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;qemu_riscv64/32&lt;/code&gt;, struggle with building the application with littlefs or with interacting with the filesystem. I have found that real hardware (i.e., the ESP32) works the best for building and running the application. However, the application still fails two coverage tests (&lt;code&gt;cover_wrap&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;cover_back&lt;/code&gt;) in the provided CMake tests. Therefore, I will have to look into OpenOCD so I can get a debugger running. On the other hand, I’m able to pass all the tests not involving file i/o on native_sim, likely since there are differences between the C libraries on &lt;code&gt;native_sim&lt;/code&gt; and other platforms (e.g., I think I am able to include header files on my system but not in the Zephyr libc). Another factor to keep in mind is that I also decreased the parameters for max LZ77 window bits and default memory level to avoid a heap overflow on my ESP32. Lastly, I have a few remarks on the Kconfig option &lt;code&gt;CONFIG_POSIX_API&lt;/code&gt;. Although this &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.zephyrproject.org/latest/services/portability/posix/overview/index.html&#34;&gt;page&lt;/a&gt; states that the option should not be used for new Zephyr applications, the truth is that &lt;code&gt;unistd.h&lt;/code&gt; still uses a &lt;code&gt;#ifdef CONFIG_POSIX_API&lt;/code&gt; block around some important functions like &lt;code&gt;read()&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;write()&lt;/code&gt;, etc. Therefore, I have set the option as a dependency for zlib.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Week 1: PDFio and zlib</title>
      <link>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/posts/week1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2025 18:05:27 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/posts/week1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Now that this inaugural week is done, I have some time to reflect on what I’ve learned and what did/did not go well. I’ve learned that I definitely work best at the beginning of my day, as I can basically devote my time entirely to the project for a few hours before dealing with other things and working more intermittently throughout pretty much the rest of the day. However, there are some things that can distract me from keeping up the momentum for those first few hours. Therefore, I think that starting work earlier and adapting my environment to be free of those distractions is something I should look towards.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Porting Printing to Zephyr</title>
      <link>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/posts/intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 15:17:36 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/posts/intro/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;OpenPrinting and Zephyr&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://HubertYGuan.github.io/GSoC-2025/images/openprintingzephyr.png#center&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;about-the-project&#34;&gt;About the Project&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Printers are a technology that we often think should “just work,” but in reality, there are often many hoops to jump through when dealing with a printer’s drivers. It is a common experience when dealing with printers to struggle to get a document printed when trying every which way on an OS like modern Windows, but then all the problems suddenly disappear when using an Apple device. This is in large part thanks to Apple’s AirPrint, which is the oldest and most widely supported driverless printing protocol. The driverless nature is important as it prevents the issue of having printer drivers that may not be updated to support the user’s current operating system. However, AirPrint is not an open standard, and only Apple operating systems are designed with it in mind. This leads us to IPP Everywhere, a driverless printing protocol that is an open standard, and its pivotal role in the modern open-source printing stack developed by OpenPrinting. This would theoretically allow any operating system that supports the printing stack to print, as long as the printer supports IPP Everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
